soft engineering radio episode 105
retrospectives with Lindauer rising this
is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at s e - radio dotnet SE radio
prints irrelevant and detailed
discussions and interviews on soft
engineering topics every 10 days thanks
to our audience and the partners listed
on our web site for supporting the hot
rod
[Music]
okay welcome listeners to another
episode of software engineering radio
another episode recorded at Q Khan and
have to say thanks for the Microsoft
folks because the room we are in is
officially paid for by Microsoft for
whatever they want to do with it anyway
so today we're going to talk to Linda
rising and so welcome Linda to the show
I'm very happy to be here and I agree
this is a wonderful room it has a
beautiful view yeah air conditioning is
a little bit loud but beautiful London
okay so Linda why don't you introduce
yourself to our listeners okay I'm in
Linda rising I live in Phoenix Arizona
which is a long way from London mm-hmm
the weather there in Phoenix is about 75
degrees Fahrenheit and it's a little bit
chillier here in London I'm an
independent consultant and my primary
interests are patterns retrospect is
agile development processes and the
change process and I've recently become
interested in primates
you mean like Apes like Apes okay and
the brain okay so I'm willing to talk
about any or all of those things okay so
that the plan for today you know we
always we're you know serious podcast we
always prepare script well a couple of
questions and those are basically around
retrospectives because you're a really
uh Authority there I might say I enjoy
I'm an advocate for retrospectives and
in fact in a month I'll be coming back
to this part of the world for the annual
retrospectives gathering there is a
conference on it time yes it's a it's a
very small conference it reminds me in a
way of the patterns conferences that
you're familiar with you so these are
people who are serious advocates for the
process and we meet in a very informal
way once a year so this is our sixth I
think an annual gathering okay so I'm
sure going to be in bath that's outside
of them about it
okay so why don't you give us the quick
overview about what retrospectives are
and then we can get into the details so
a retrospective is a time for reflection
mm-hmm
and typically what's done is to decide
what you're going to use as the focus of
that reflection so if we're talking
about software development typically an
agile project would take time for
reflection at the end of each iteration
then again a full project retrospective
at the end of the project but it's
something that is a practice that can be
applied to anything in fact those of us
who are true advocates for the practice
feel this is something you should do in
your own life okay you should take time
to think about what's working well what
should be done differently mm-hmm so
that is basically these two of those
four magic questions that demands yes
the first one is what's working well
that we want to make sure we remember
going forward for the next iteration if
we're talking about an iteration
retrospective not just what's working
well but the startling things that we've
uncovered in fact I tend to think of
development nowadays as a series of
experiments so each iteration is an
experiment what is it that we're
experimenting with the purpose of the
retrospective then becomes to examine
the results of that experiment so what
worked well about that experiment that
we don't want to forget going forward
and then what should we do differently
and that's really going to define the
experiment for the next iteration what
did we learn from all of this maybe
there are larger lessons than just some
sort of specific technique what are
larger things that we learned in the
process and the final question is what
puzzles us and those are mysteries that
we have no way of answering or
addressing but what we find is that by
capturing those we may become closer to
a solution or I like to think of puzzles
a message for higher level management
right managers often come in to look at
the results of retrospectives and when
they see a puzzle
something like why do we always promise
the customer that we will have this
delivered in two weeks when we know at
the outset that there's no way we're
going to make that why do we continue to
do that that's a puzzle yeah but don't
really have an answer for that and I
think as a manager I would like to see
those puzzles and it also gives the
developers a sense of satisfaction that
we're not just throwing those away we
really care about those and at some
point we might find a solution for that
mystery so it is it fair to say that
it's fundamentally of a way of
optimizing the development process and
the coherence of the team I suppose you
could say that because retrospectives
serve many purposes it's not only about
answering those four questions with
respect to the development process it's
about getting together as a group and
when the group examines what happened in
the last iteration they understand that
they didn't see everything they need to
have a shared experience where I can say
what I saw you can say what you saw and
we learn from that experience it's a
great team-building exercise and you
know there are things that we don't talk
about in a normal course of our work
things about how we felt right things
about where we were disappointed things
about things in our personal lives
things that don't come out at any other
time so it's an opportunity to talk
about a lot of issues yeah and and as
you said in the context of the
iterations it's it's for me it's pretty
clear that that retrospectives are an
essential part of agile processes it's
probably not closely tied you could do
retrospectives in other environments
they might not be as effective but yes
and in fact I began doing retrospectives
with and in a company where we were
doing a mixture of agile projects and
traditional waterfall and
all the projects were doing some form of
retrospective I think the thing that's
new is norm curse book does call out the
term retrospective and he put a
different slant on the process but
certainly the process has been with us
for millennia right the military it was
a leader I mean Lee they the military
has been doing retrospectives forever
and rightly so
lives are on the line they care about
improving they care about doing things
better next time so there's always a
retrospective done in any military
organization it's called debriefing yes
and they all might have different names
for it post project review firefighters
do it any any time there is criticality
involved lives are on the line there is
some sort of meeting or gathering where
they discuss these questions or other
similar questions so it's certainly a
process that can be applied to many
different domains so let's let's bring
it back to software development because
I mean we were software engineering
radio so let's talk a little bit about
the logistics you already said something
about when to do it so one thing is
doing it at the end of an iteration yes
and what else well first of all we can
talk about that part of it because when
people hear about doing a retrospective
often they're concerned about the
penalty you know it's the illusion that
a lot of the practices and agile
development seem to penalize development
pair programming is another example of
that penalizing sends off that it looks
like it makes things less efficient
because you put two people in front of
yes exactly well I have two people doing
the work of one person and until you've
actually been there it's hard to be
convinced of the benefit so there is a
penalty to doing a retrospective often
if you're gonna do one at the end of
each iteration the first thing that
comes to mind is well the tremendous
cost you're saying we're gonna take time
every two weeks to do this exercise well
how long does that take are we talking
about three or four days no no we're
talking about something that's very
short but is an investment
yeah and the penalty really is in not
doing the retrospective that what comes
out of it is the true learning you know
I often say when I'm talking about
retrospectives that we suffer under the
illusion that we learn from experience
just by having the experience we learn
so I always tell the story of a friend
of mine who's been married five times
well surely she learned along the way
yeah she should be improving or the
other example I often give is if you
believe that you really learn from
experience then you've never made the
same mistake twice
is that really true yeah so we do need
something some way of examining the
experience some way of determining that
we should do things differently not to
beat ourselves up and to say that we
were stupid but to learn in going
forward to say now that didn't work so
well what are we gonna do differently
and so there is an investment but the
benefit can be tremendous and that the
team does really learn from the
experience it is not automatic and and
since you mentioned the length I guess I
would say the more often you do it the
fault of each of them will become so
it's that happened that in the
retrospective runs for two days it can
and in fact most of the time when people
don't do them very often well then
there's a lot a lot of material to
examine and a lot of material to cover
but if you do it regularly every two
weeks it's what we call a heartbeat
retrospective there is a sense that a
project that is working well has a
heartbeat it has a rhythm and the
retrospective in that case can maybe
take an hour or less just like a scrum
meeting done well it really has no
penalty doesn't take long at all yep so
who should participate well the answer
to that is anyone who should participate
sure but how do we find how do I find
out I mean that one of the questions
that's being asked is do I involve
management yes that's always the
question that's
asked and the answer is it depends I
believe that everybody who cares about
the project you might say the
stakeholders all stakeholders should be
there but to be realistic for an
iteration retrospective it's difficult
to get everybody in the room at the same
time and in many cases it might not be
the best thing for the manager to be
there why because what you want to hear
in a retrospective is the truth and you
want people to feel safe and you want
them to be able to tell the truth so
they're all the people in retrospective
should be peers or equals in that sense
and not you know with their oversight
person in their Lee and in many cases
the developers are perfectly comfortable
with having the manager there so if I
were coming in from the outside to lead
a retrospective which typically would
not happen for an iteration
retrospective no someone else outside
the team would lead it because you do
need an external facilitator but you
don't need to bring in someone who's
outside the larger organization right
but if I were coming in and I didn't
know the team and I didn't know the
comfort level with having anyone the
manager the customer the product owner
whatever the other roles are I would do
an exercise some very something very
simple the one that norm Kurth
recommends is called create safety yeah
and in that one you anonymously ask for
feedback to determine how comfortable
are you with the people in the room and
you ask people to evaluate on a scale of
one to four or one to five and they'll
tell you and if they're not comfortable
in another round of that exercise they
might tell you why is it the manager is
it's a customer is it the new guy is it
the old grizzled veteran who's going to
make comments that make so you can just
simply ask as long as they are given
anonymously to a facilitator is not on
the team right that's why this is
important the team that is not on the
team and that they write it on a card
and you collect the cards so it's it's
outlined in Norma's book but what I find
when I do that exercise is I'm often
surprised
that teams that seemed perfectly safe
were not not yes and teams that seemed a
little dysfunctional we're perfectly
safe and felt free to tell the truth so
if we talk about this moderator
type what kind of skills does this
person need to have I mean since you're
doing this as a service is probably for
hire
then there is probably a reason why
people get you and not everybody so what
is what is that what do you think are
the key qualifications for being a good
moderator well you're looking at
facilitation skills you want to make
sure that there is an agenda that is
followed that there are guidelines for
the meeting just as there are guidelines
for any meeting that people turn their
cell phones off that no one speaks when
someone else is speaking so there are
general guidelines that um every meeting
should follow and then for the
retrospective well one thing we're very
always very careful about is to follow
norm curse prime directive which is
which basically says that we are going
to proceed believing that everyone on
the team did the best job he or she
could now of course we've learned we
were better at everything now than we
were at the beginning but given what we
knew at the time right and what we faced
what the situation was and our
understanding of it given all of that we
want to believe at least for the sake of
the retrospective that everyone was
doing the best job he or she could so
this is not a session about blaming I'm
not okay this is not a time to lay
problems at the feet of an individual so
the rule we try to follow in addition to
all the other meeting guidelines is no
naming okay you can talk about any
problem you want but it don't you don't
say you you don't say even if everyone
on the team understands that when you're
talking about a particular problem that
you are talking about an individual so
you can say for instance that database
was late and everyone knows that Marcus
was working on the database but there is
a tremendous difference
between saying the database was late
[Music]
what can we do to make sure that doesn't
happen what can we learn from that and
instead saying Marcus screwed up we
would have been buying if it weren't for
Marcus so of course words make a
difference words make a difference in
how the team focuses on what's to be
done
we're not concentrating on getting rid
of Marcus we're concentrating on saying
what should be done differently to make
sure that we don't have to address this
same problem again
so is it useful or necessary at least
for the somewhat bigger retrospectives
to do them off-site well you know
there's a there's a pattern in the
Fairless change book that Kevin Hanny
wrote it's called animation location
location he wrote the pattern because I
think you wrote the book wrote the book
well we put we put the book together but
it's a book of patterns and you know
patterns are run by a community and
they're workshopped by a community so
there's the list of contributors is
enormous and that that pattern
originated so he was the originator of
the pattern location Location Location
and what it says is that for all things
that you care about where you hold that
meeting that retrospective that training
class now does make a difference people
feel about the experience that it's
special right or they put more effort
into it or they're more careful about
the results away from their emails just
away from things so they can't quickly
run back and have a quick meeting it
does make a difference where it is but
unfortunately the reality of the
corporate environment today there isn't
time there isn't the budget and if
you're talking about a meeting that
happens every two weeks yeah I mean it's
much more difficult yeah but I guess for
those things if they're only one hour
long something's probably not necessary
no and I think there are other things
you can do to make my meeting special
like I'm a big believer in food and you
bet because I read your book this was
one of the cornerstones of me
meetings mice it's fundamental to human
interaction we're hardwired to behave
toward each other as we were in the
Stone Age and what we learned there is
that the people that we break bread with
are the people we trust
and you might say good heavens
Linda you you live in the country that
has the fattest people on the face of
the earth surely food is not something
that people really care about anymore
but we're hardwired and we respond to
those chocolate chip cookies so if
they're on the table it makes a
difference in the meeting so that's
something you can do to make the meeting
special without spending a lot of money
and without hauling the group right to
an expensive off-site location so assume
I would hire you for a retrospective of
one of my customers I've actually been
thinking about that they weren't they
weren't interested what do I have to
prepare what do we expect the team
you're going to to collect they you know
what what what do you have to do in
order for you to be effective with a
retrospective or anybody else you know
the answer to that is it depends because
a lot of times teams that call me in our
teams that are having struggles I don't
often get called in when things are
going well it's when there's been a big
problem and so what I get is the story
of the team I might get some contact
information from people who were on the
team or who were stakeholders of various
kinds so that I can have a little email
discussion or a little phone
conversation or maybe Skype with them to
say well what what do you think can
happen what should I think about and
then of course the people who are
calling me and the supporters of the
retrospective have expectations so I
always have some kind of interaction
with them to say can you tell me what
you're looking for what do you expect to
find what do you suspect a problem could
be all kinds of information anything
that might be of interest to me and if
it's a company that I already know well
because there are times when I go back
to especially large companies that I
know a little bit about the culture so I
can ask some questions that lead me to
believe whether there might be an issue
with safety or not sometimes you don't
have to do the safety exercise sometimes
you already know you know and sometimes
they'll send you some project documents
a little bit of the history what was
this project all about since I am a
developer myself I spent a long time in
development I'm interested in that I
would like to know that was going on and
I learned myself
when I go in to do a retrospective I
learn a tremendous amount but you want
to be paid of course of course I want to
be paid so the answer is it depends the
answer is it depends on how much time
sometimes it is a last-minute decision
and I walk in without a lot of pre-work
and so I try to get as much as I can and
I try to encourage the people on the
team to have a little bit of an
understanding of what's going to happen
so I want to know what they you know
about introspective I want to encourage
them to think about what happened over
the 6 months or the two years or how
long it's been since they had a
retrospective I want to encourage them
to participate in the artifacts contest
which is one of my favorite exercises so
that takes a little preparation they
need to think back and then bring in an
object to the retrospective so I want to
make sure they know what is going to
happen so I'm going to prepare them a
little bit and in the future what they
can do is they can listen to this
episode service to the world yep
wonderful so since we already mentioned
that how does a retrospective typically
precede other like distinct phases or I
mean is it like a ritual in some sense
well there are phases to a retrospective
and sometimes you can include all the
phases and you know in an our
retrospective for a team that does them
off and you don't need to necessarily
cover
all the phases but for a project
retrospective that most and that's
mostly what I see yes so I talked about
a project retrospective that the initial
state is sage is called the readying you
get people prepared for the
retrospective and that would mean going
over the guidelines make sure they
understood the impact of the prime
directive make sure that they had maybe
they have their own set of meeting
guidelines or things that they typically
follow we might look at the create
safety exercise see if there are any
safety issues before we start and then
the next phase is typically called
looking back it's looking at the history
so this is something that's been running
for six months we want to talk about
what happened and the problem with that
is that our memory spans these days are
awfully short and I say that not because
I'm getting older but because we are all
under a lot of stress and we multitask
and we can't remember what happened
yesterday
let alone what happened six months ago
so there are a series of exercise and
norms book and also in Diana and
Esther's book which I'm probably going
to talk about so there are lots of
exercises that help people remember so
that's in the looking back phase and
then you're doing all of this because
you want to plan so there are sets of
exercises that you can do to get ready
we want to take action based on what we
learned by looking back so preparing for
the future looking forward deciding what
what kinds of things who will take those
action items so there are basically
those three phases preparation looking
back looking forward mm-hm
so then let's take a look at some of
those practices or games and maybe steps
through a couple of them and see three
and maybe the way we do this and just
like if we discuss a patterns book I
will kind of you know like I will just
mention one of the names of those
practice and you can I can say something
about it of course everybody knows that
we prepared that so
so the first one is that I didn't like
write down all of them from the norms
book but the ones that I thought are
from my experience as a participant and
certainly there are some I I like and I
use more than others yep yeah and tell
us
yeah which those are so the first one I
wrote down is to define success yes it's
one of my favorites so right I start
almost I'm trying to think of there's an
exception in my mind that's how I start
and from what I've been learning about
the brain because remember that was one
of the things I was interested in that
will talk about that program yes the
brain is that it makes a difference how
you start and the first thing you think
of because our tendency I used to think
this was a characteristic of engineers
but it's a human characteristic our
tendency is to be critical and it's so
easy it's so easy for us to find all of
the things that were wrong and so to set
the tone for the retrospective I like
the define success exercise what does it
do I begin by saying asking the people
in the room to pretend that you're
walking down the hallway of this
organization and you run into someone
you haven't seen for a while and that
person says to you ah I hear you've been
working on that project well how is that
going and I want you to pretend that you
reply to them that's great that project
is really great
because and now what I capture on the
flip chart is the rest of that sentence
it's great because now sometimes it's so
difficult for a team especially if
they've been through a failed project
that has had some struggles they will
sit there for a moment and nothing will
be forthcoming so you know you've got to
give it a little time
but it's never failed that once somebody
says something only you and I know what
a writer's workshop is I was about to
mention that because that also starts
with looking at the positive aspect yes
and how many times have I gone into a
writer's workshop with a paper I wasn't
really fond of and I thought what am I
going to say what am I going to say but
again I always find that when it starts
someone will offer a positive comment
and I think to myself well yes that's
right that that was good and now that
makes me think of something else and
exactly the same thing happens in define
success as soon as someone steps forward
and invariably someone will say
something and it's usually about the
team yeah this was a great group of
people yeah the project was crude but we
like each other and when that comes out
then others will follow it and in a real
retrospective you let that go as long as
it goes so I use what I call the
microwave popcorn test you know when you
put microwave popcorn and it goes pop
pop pop pop pop up oh I see it's time to
take it out yes so you don't wait
forever just to make sure you have all
possible comments you let it go a
reasonable amount of time and what
you've done with that is set the stage
what so people are now thinking just as
they are in a workshop mm-hmm you're
thinking about the good things and it's
okay now to move on to other things
so the next part of the exercise is to
say norm Kurth in his book project
retrospectives says wow you know so many
positive things this must have been a
success mm-hmm
but I think my definition of success
would be that people on the project
would say I would do this over again in
exactly the same
you let that sit for a minute mm-hmm and
you can tell that everyone in the room
is saying no no I don't think so for
that yeah so even on the most successful
project there are always a few things
that we would do differently if we had
to do it over again so the question is
not all the bad things we're not asking
for that
but what we're asking is what would you
do differently and that also sets the
tone for the retrospective which is we
are not here to whine and complain we're
here to learn and our approach is almost
called retrospective yes it's our our
purpose is to say looking forward based
on our experience what would we do
differently yeah so it this is not the
end of the retrospective sometimes
people think well that's it we can no
it's just getting people thinking and
framing which is another brain thing
framing the kinds of things we want to
hear so it's all of the good things and
what would you do differently so again
you capture those microwave popcorn
tents and now you have those on the wall
and you can always point back to those
but it's a very good way to start
and let me say by the way that these
exercises that are in norms book come
from dysfunctional family therapy
honestly yes honestly so you wonder how
is it that the connection was made
between dysfunctional families and
software teams cool okay so so the next
one I wrote down is timeline and that's
probably a way of going back these six
months and remembering stuff explicitly
right yes and I love timelines I keep
thinking maybe I'll find a better way to
go back but that that is the best way in
a timeline
is simply a large space it can be on the
wall but often I'm in an environment
where you can't use the wall we can't
put a pin or a piece of tape or anything
else on the wall
so I've done time lines on tables on the
floor just has to be a large space and
so you divide the large space up into a
series of events so that everyone
understands what the points are on the
time line so they might simply be
January February March they might be
first quarter second quarter third
quarter they might be milestones it's I
leave that up to the team how do you
want to divide the time line up and then
we use a collection of colored cards the
cards are all anonymous and people write
on them what happened as far as they're
concerned what the significant events
were and then the colors reflect how
they felt about that particular event so
one of the events might have been and
since we mentioned it already that
database was late yep
so if the person was angry about that
they would write it on a red card if
they were angry or frustrated or upset
put it on a red card maybe they were
working on something and they were late
and they knew that as long as the
database was delayed their stuff was
okay so they were happy about that so
they might write it on a blue card to
say our sky is blue I'm happy the
database is late okay so you can see the
same event on different colors the other
two that I use are yellow for surprise
that means well we didn't expect this
but we're not upset about it and green
for challenge people use a variety of
colors people don't use colors but what
you get with colors is you can stand
back from the time line
mm-hmm and now you can see how were
people at the beginning is it all blue
and then you have them talk about just
what does that look like to you what do
you see and they can see for themselves
oh this is where yep this is where the
red came in or it started as yellow a
few yellow surprises that became red and
then we had that bad third quarter and
then it's a little bit like building
team memory yes yes because you have
people continuously write cards post-it
is my father thinking about things so
they read what's on the timeline and
then they that helps them remember and
when the popcorn tests again you don't
see too many cards then we do something
like the artifacts contest sort of in
the middle you mentioned that before
already it's bringing stuff in yes it's
about bringing in any object so you ask
people beforehand to think back and to
bring in what for them was a significant
object and it could be here's a copy of
the original schedule remember that
remember the party we had at the end of
the first quarter when things were going
well and we got t-shirts and we got
little rubber ducks because of something
to do with a project I don't you don't
always get to decide jokes and somebody
has some of those little rubber ducks
and people look at that like oh I
remember and it's exactly what happens
at Christmas when you unpack the
ornaments and you see something that
your daughter made when she was three
years old and it's made of glittery
stuff and macaroni and all of a sudden
you remember you remember her when she
was three years old so somebody brings
in the little rubber duck and he's oh
yeah I remember that party and now I
remember some other things that should
go on the timeline ah so you use the
artifact contest as I see so I see
in the middle a good help and so now a
few more cards go up and people are now
remembering more things and people tell
a story about the spring yes exactly so
and sometimes it's funny yeah sometimes
it's sad but now they're the team itself
is there's sort of remembering together
or as when they started the timeline
they were each working individually so
it starts to bring them together and the
next exercise we're still in the middle
of the timeline is called offer
appreciations okay and for that I just
asked them to take a seat and usually we
sit in a little circle and the rules are
that you can say to someone Marcus I
remember when you stayed over that
weekend I remember it now you stayed
over that weekend before the first
customer demo and if you hadn't been
here all weekend working on those
remember those two big errors the thing
kept blowing up we wouldn't have been
able to do that demo but but I also
remember that you missed your son's
birthday party I'm not sure didn't we
ever say thank you for that yeah thank
you and thank you I appreciate that you
did that for the team and now somebody
will remember something else and you let
that go as long as it goes yeah way
beyond the microwave test okay be on
okay so you want sometimes people are
reluctant yeah and they will hang back
but they need to say that they need to
get that out and I've seen grizzled
veterans little tears I've seen people
who were not too happy about the whole
thing the retrospective the team I've
seen them sort of come in and join the
team in offer appreciations so it's such
a powerful exercise and I close that by
saying there's no reason why you have to
wait for a retrospective to do that
yeah you should do that all the time yep
just appreciate each other so so this
thing is obviously quite a bit emotional
it can be very emotional which is the
perfect segue into the next thing we
wrote down which is called emotion sighs
emotion emotion seismogram and of course
after each one of these after the
artifacts contest and after offer
appreciations we put more cards on the
wall the timeline is still going yeah
that's something you do in parallel to
some of those things yeah because we
haven't finished it yet and the
seismograph is underneath the timeline
you save a little bit of space at the
bottom maybe two feet or so and you ask
people to if they could draw a little
bit like an EKG or an electrocardiogram
that would say at this point in the
timeline how are you feeling so the top
of the seismographs is I'm so happy to
be here I I wouldn't want to be anywhere
else and the very bottom is how fast can
I find another job and everybody does it
and then you get a kind of aggregate
curve they just draw a little curve that
runs along the bottom and you can see
where the highs and lows were for
individuals whether they're the same or
different and it kind of gives you a
picture of what you have with the
timeline and the seismograph is you have
a story of the project itself so once
you've done all of that then the
timeline is is ready for the next phase
you've done what you can do I usually
have after everything is up I ask people
to walk the wall if they haven't - make
sure they've read every single card and
to go back in their minds to remember
what happened that's so that's the end
of the timeline okay okay
four more of those things the next one
would be mindful gold so now you've got
the timeline and now what you want to do
is build on those comments and over time
I've kind of changed the way I do that
but what I ask people to do is take
those cards and let's put them in
categories so we have sort of a mind map
of what were we talking about what are
we talking about are there a lot of
database problems are there some testing
problems are there some customer
interaction problems
I don't classify that I asked them to do
it and so we cluster them and then we
label each one of those categories so
what we're trying to do is pull out from
the time line what are the actions going
forward and to identify issues that need
to be addressed and while that's going
on people might add more cards why is
this called mine for gold what you're
trying to do is pull out you know what
miners do they go underground and they
dig and they have to go through a lot of
dirt to actually pull up the nuggets and
so the process begins that way but we're
far from finished we have to examine
those categories now so I ask for
volunteers and they self select to work
on the category and to decide can we
pull out some action items can we pull
out some lessons learned what what can
we do to mine this category and so we
split up so we can do that in parallel
depends on the size of the team how many
categories there are how you how you do
that and also is if this is a project
retrospective how much time do we have
right so we spend a certain amount of
time on that and then each team reports
back here the Nuggets right here's the
gold they found in this process Gold
being the action items for the next the
potential may potentially the potential
action items from the process okay yes
change to paper change the paper is not
an exercise I do but what what it means
is that we're going to look at what was
done and we're going to and if you
continue the way I was working we need
to look at what happened to decide what
we're gonna do differently so we would
sort of begin to capture all of those
suggestions and now we need to narrow
them down right so there are lots of
ways of doing that and again it depends
on is this a team that's going to stay
together
will they really be able to take actions
is there going to be a following release
for instance so that we really can't
assign people action items otherwise if
we just make a list and nobody does
anything it's kind of a waste of time
yeah so what happens next depends upon
the character of the organization pretty
much change the paper means let's do
something differently going forward and
write a letter that's fine I don't
letter now where did you get that I'm
not sure it is I think that's an
exercise that I did that I created on
the spot maybe and I presented that one
of the things we do at the
retrospectives gathering is we talk
about new ideas for exercises and one
year I had done a retrospective for a
team that was severely depressed we did
the retrospective at the end of a period
when they knew they were all going to be
taken off of the project and weren't
even sure whether they were still going
to have a job with the company it was
going to be out sourced you know this is
an old story now it was going to be out
sourced and so there was no way to hand
an action item forward so we've gone
through all of this and suddenly because
I didn't really understand that and Here
I am in the middle of the retrospective
realizing that these people don't care
mm-hmm they're leaving they're either
gonna have another job or they're gonna
be assigned to a different project and
the whole thing is going to India or
China or someplace so you write the
letter to the guy who's continuing the
project so that I mean it was one of
those moments where the muse descends
and I thought I gotta find a way out of
this because we can't have action items
what are we going to do this so I gave
them each some paper and I said I know
you'll never meet the people on the team
but just imagine someone imagine someone
on the other team and sit down and tell
them from your point of view whatever
your role was on the team pretend you're
talking to the person who will have that
role on the other team and write them a
letter that tells them your thoughts
about what went on your thoughts about
what should happen and so I tried to
inspire them by saying you know I'm
closer to the end of my life than the
beginning and I know that at some point
I'm going to die but that doesn't mean
that I don't care about what happens in
the world but that doesn't mean that I
might not have some last words of wisdom
based on my experience that I would be
happy to share just because I care about
what goes on with other human beings
because that concern lasts I think until
you have your last breath so I said you
could think of yourself in that way that
you're you're dying with respect to this
project that doesn't mean you don't care
about the that other person it's not
their fault you're getting laid off that
it's not their fault that things didn't
go well so think of this as one person
talking to another let me tell you what
I can yeah and I thought well we'll see
how this goes and it was so surprising
because they just wrote and wrote and
wrote and they were just pouring out
their hearts and then in the meantime
the project manager came back and he
said what are you doing
and I said they're writing letters to
the people and the other team and he is
brilliant brilliant so he he promised to
the team he said I will make sure that
these letters are all delivered to the
people on the new team I promise you
that yeah this is I think an important
point I think that you really need to
follow up on yes you do there I mean you
know really make sure they actually the
action items are executed and you know
just make the people feel that what they
did in the retrospect is a great
retrospective actually is useful yes
absolutely otherwise they won't believe
right and that would yes although I have
seen retrospectives we're just having it
was good in the reflects they got to go
through it and the story I tell is about
a team that that was fact in fact my
first retrospective where the team put
up an enormous timeline and when you see
that what they get out of walking up and
down the timeline and standing in little
groups talking about the cards pointing
to cards touching cards and you think
that was worth it even if nothing comes
out of it yeah
but of course it's always good to say
because we learned this we're going to
make sure that something happens are
there any other practices slash games
that you like and you like to mention
but I didn't ask you about one I like to
do at the end is called hopes and wishes
I think this is enormous book but I'm
I'm not sure it may just be something
that I adapted but I ask the team
especially if they're going forward with
another release and they're going to
stay together is to write on a card a
sentence or two that begins I hope or I
wish and it's their hope or wish for the
next release and then we collect those
and we put them in a little sealed
envelope a sort of like a time capsule
right and then at the next retrospective
we open that and we read from the hopes
and wishes and sometimes this is
optional when they're all through and I
said before I collect those would anyone
like to read a hope or a wish and
sometimes they do and so that sort of
that's the last thing we do that's
absolutely the very end of the exercises
is they're ready to walk out the door it
sort of gives them something as you know
on my way out the door I hope and then
their hope or wish so it's a good way to
close so we already
covered this idea that a retrospective
is not a blaming exercise yes there is
another prejudice or misconception or
problem that I could imagine and that is
that the participants think those
practices and games are childish yes
what do you say to those people the
games are always optional and I have led
retrospectives where some people would
not participate mm-hmm
in fact the the example that comes to
mind was a team that I led where
obviously there were some problems this
was not a failed project but a project
that did not deliver successfully and it
was held off-site and we had catered
lunch so the company obviously spent a
fair amount of money on this and when
they came in they were all late so
that's kind of a signal right there they
came in late they obviously didn't care
about what was going on and one
individual in particular did not sit
with the rest of the team Wow
so he sat in the corner strong signal he
sat in the corner he would not
participate and everything that we did
was kind of a joke people I there was a
joke to everybody okay
and so we were building the timeline and
now they were writing silly comments and
putting them on the wall so obviously
they had had some problems so we did the
artifacts contest and they hadn't
brought any central they didn't care so
I thought well we try offer
appreciations so I said well here's how
this game works well they thought it was
really hilarious now this is going to be
so funny so then somebody started said
well all right I want to thank and it
was kind of a joke thing I want to thank
so-and-so for you know doing something
and everybody laughed and then the next
one was a little more serious said well
you know I'm thinking back to something
and all of a sudden
it happened while he was speaking that
they all it was Oh they'd been
sleepwalking and they woke up we
remember we remember what this was all
about and we remember that at one time
we cared and in fact for that individual
he could not finish his appreciation he
got and it's hard for me to watch that
because I sit off to the side and I get
really involved with these guys and I'm
sitting there think I can't cry I have
to maintain my level of professional you
know not not and not be involved but he
couldn't finish and it was clear that he
was on the verge of tears and so he just
he just stopped and I said it's all
right you can finish your appreciation
later and that just changed the tone for
the whole thing and and then someone
else spoke and then the guy in the
corner he came in and he said I just
want to say thank you for putting up
with me and he sat down so what I
learned from that was sometimes we get
into a role or a place you know like I'm
the skeptic I'm the old guy I'm the one
who doesn't care I'm the one who always
makes fun of everything I'm the you know
whatever it is and then we realize that
we're not happy there and we can't get
out right I know that so one thing that
can happen and and since I've seen that
now
several times since that is it in a
retrospective you are almost offering
people a chance to really change who
they are what their role is on the team
and that the whole team can sort of
shuffle itself and when they walk out
it's not the same team that walked in
and I'm not enough of a therapist to
understand
what it is all I know is I've seen it
and that it was astounding to me that
these exercises the way they're
structured and obviously if they are
based on dysfunctional family therapy
that they're there for a reason and that
they call to people to say it's okay you
can say the truth and you can be
somebody that you want to be and that
that's so much more powerful than I
thought a retrospective was ever all
about it's always a revelation to me so
how do I convince management I mean I
really need to know this it's a very
selfish question I said I have this
customer so I mean how do I if
management's things okay yeah well it's
just one of those other agile hype
things I mean except for having people
listen to this episode or or call you
and let you tell them what do I do to
convince especially skeptical managers
who don't want to pay or spend the time
so my experience is that management does
see the benefits ahead of the technical
staff okay that they know that there's a
benefit to trying to learn from your
experience I mean most managers have
heard knowledge management or a learning
organization and so they run into issues
like that at their level all the time
and they don't have any idea how to make
that happen and it's the technical
people who usually see what why do we
have to spend time getting together for
another meeting where we talk about
stuff I mean they're the ones who are
the most difficult to convince it the
managers and especially high-level
managers it's the people who pay for
things or who authorized payment they
are usually the easiest to sell if you
just tell them a little bit about what
goes on and the purpose of it is
learning and that you want to improve
you know have constant
improvement they know what the
importance of those things and here's
the real benefit for especially higher
level managers is that you can say you
know when we finish this we'll have a
lot of information
we'll have timelines will have flip
charts full of stuff and you can come
into the room
once it's done when it's done and you
can read all of those comments on the
cards and you can see what got put on
the flip charts now that's appealing
because it's a way for them to really
hear the voice of the people who are on
the bottom because when they ask for
information it's often filtered through
three or four layers and by the time
they get the story of what happened on
Project X it's so far removed from the
real experience they never hear the
truth so what you can offer them is a
chance to hear the voices of the people
on the team telling it as they saw it
and if they're not interested in that I
guess there is a Depot problem yeah
there is probably but you know my
experience is of course I I'm I'm
talking about the organizations that
call me in so yes so they they do they
have some interested in it but
nonetheless they're not necessarily sure
how it's all about to work out but at
the end of the day these high-level
individuals will come into the room and
here you've got walls covered with stuff
or cards all over the table they will
read everything you can say well now
here are the piles of cards that we took
they will pick up every single card I
mean every card and if we have them on
the floor they'll get down on their
knees and read every I mean every flip
chart you can say oh well these are the
thing and they go right up to the wall
they look at every bullet and sometimes
they'll go back these are busy people
who don't have a lot of time they'll go
and they'll take notes they're really
interested in what comes out of a
retrospective I didn't and that was
something again I didn't realize until I
had seen it for myself there our
relationship to continuous improvement
like CMM stuff is it is it in I mean you
are in a way continuously improving your
team in your process and the way you
work I don't think you can be at a
higher CMM level than one unless you are
doing some form of retrospective and the
higher you go the more a part of your
process it has to be it might not be
called a retrospective and there might
not be the connect the deep connection
what norm has done for the software
development community but there is
certainly some pretty well defined
process that says we've got to go back
and learn from our experience so in
order for people to help them to learn
more about retrospectives I think we
have to solve the the norm question who
is this guy why did you messed it all
the time norm curse you know what's
interesting about this conference is
that the ones we are yeah where we are
as Q con is that I'm continually struck
by the number of presenters and keynote
speakers who are big names or important
people in the agile software development
community who were also major
contributors to the patterns community
so Kent Beck Martin Fowler Eric gamma
and norm curse was also a member of the
patterns community we had my first
shepherd was he so I the only thing the
patterns community contributed an
enormous amount to the entire software
development community not only as
patterns but an agile and and in other
areas as well so norm curse I met in the
patterns community and
he was he he was not a shepherd for me
ever but when I did my first
retrospective it was because we were
doing design patterns and I was a
patterns person and we had a failure an
enormous failure and so my manager came
to see me and he said I don't know what
the connection is but the whole company
realizes that this was something that
had major impact and so we think there
might be patterns here in the sense that
their patterns of things we don't want
to do so that was before anti-pattern he
said can't you find out whether there
are patterns here that's how I got
involved in retrospective and I said
I'll try but I don't know how to begin
and I knew norm was working on this now
there was no book at the time but norm
led me through it he was the one who
outlined what we should do with this
project and how we could find out and we
did did find patterns
that's how I met norm I got to know him
very well
and at that time and he was working on
the book project retrospectives which is
kind of the standard it is the only book
on a project retrospectives ester Derby
and Diana Larson have written a book on
agile retrospectives
and it builds on norms book okay so it's
sort of Taylor's the retrospective
process to the shorter iterative or we
call it heartbeat retrospectives
so it in no way displaces it right it is
equally valuable you need them both
preserve a lot of papers if you go to my
website and we will probably have a link
to them what's your website and the book
ok so if you go to my website the I've
written several articles on
retrospectives and it's a that's a good
place to start because it doesn't cost
anything salt a little bit it's shorter
and they'll give you a kind of an
overview and and Esther and I wrote an
article for cutter on the combination
that I see between retrospectives and
patterns
and one of the valuable things if you do
it in your own organization I can't do
it anymore because I only go in as an
isolated outsider I go in I do the
retrospective I leave but if you do them
across projects in an organization after
a while you can begin to see patterns
and they're the patterns for your
organization so you should begin to
document those and that that's kind of
what I moved into in the company where I
was doing design patterns all of a
sudden I'm writing patterns for project
teams which is something very new for me
so that's the book it's called project
retrospectives it was published by
Dorsett house and I think 2001 mm-hmm
it has been translated into a plethora
of languages norm had a very serious
automobile accident and he doesn't do
consulting anymore he's still a valuable
contributor to the retrospectives
community and so another resource is the
Yahoo list which is called
retrospectives I think we should
probably move that up put that in and so
if anyone appears on the on that
discussion with a question it's an open
group open okay anyone can sign up for
it so anyone who appears on there is
always surprised that at some point it
has to be when he's feeling okay that
norm will answer so he will tell you
what he thinks about yeah how cool is
that yeah and and I'm there Esther's
there
Diana's there rachel.davies is major
contributor she's somebody else who's
here she's the one who's hosting the
gathering this year even while she's
chairing agile 2008 I don't know how she
is my hero
absolutely so it's a it's a community
that's small enough I mean the patterns
community was like that I don't know
whether you remember in the beginning I
could get on the patterns discussion
listserv and I could get answers from
the Gang of Four almost before my time
John Bliss CDs that's when I first met
John
so and I miss him terribly it that that
can happen when it's small right yeah
so the Patni the patterns community is
is so much bigger now so we've kind of
lost that but the retrospectives
community is not only small but we
encourage where we try to encourage
everyone and so you have to I mean
that's what you preach it in yes so
people sign on and say I'm new to this
I'm just trying to get this going in my
company here's a problem I have and boom
boom boom you'll get answers from people
the people who write the books so I
encourage people to go sign up for that
and we'll have to look up the exact yeah
I think it's retrospectives at Yahoo dot
okay we'll find it yeah so so we're at
the end of the planned stuff okay do you
want to maybe let us know why you're
interested in brain and primates wrap
this thing up and I guess there is some
relationship to team software process I
guess I hope I think that's what you
make money with actually okay so
somebody asked me a question
just recently what's the book that most
changed or influenced your life so I've
been thinking about that and I realize
that it was the the last book I wrote
which was fearless change patterns for
introducing new ideas which may be
something we can do an episode on
sometime in the future if you're
interested I am I'm always interested in
talking about change okay I started
writing that book in 1995 and at the
time I if you had said well Linda who
are you I would have described myself as
a designer and I was interested in
design patterns and the reason I started
thinking about the patterns that are in
fearless change was because I wanted the
people in my organization the other
developers to use design patterns so I
thought there must be patterns for doing
this patterns for helping people use
patterns and that's how those patterns
started and as I began to write them I
thought well
do people solve problems I mean that
that's the benefit of a pattern is it it
helps you solve is that really the best
way I became interested in how people
solve problems in how you help other
people solve problems how I convince
other people to use my ideas to solve
their problems things I had never
thought of before things I wasn't really
interested in before in all my I have
lots of technical degrees I started out
as a chemist and I have a bachelor's
degree in chemistry with a minor in
biochemistry I was a chemist for a while
then I became a mathematician I taught
mathematics for a while and then I
became a computer scientist I have a PhD
in computer science in all of that I had
one psychology course because it was
required yeah and I hated it I thought
it was boring and I thought it was not
interesting I don't care about the
experiments so it was only later in
thinking about I want to help people use
patterns then I became interested and
now psychology has changed as my husband
says the reason you like this stuff now
is it is technical because we can
actually look at your brain oh I see we
can do functional MRIs we can do scans
it's it's it's the precise science to
this that's right and instead of talking
about theories for behavior we actually
know what parts of the brain are
involved in fear for instance in
learning that and and in fact something
I read just recently that I talked about
yesterday so you know it's it's so
exciting and it's so new is that they
can hear rat brains talking to each
other as the rats sleep so they can
actually monitor the neurons as they're
saying all right well here's how we ran
this maze today oh yeah that's right a
store that
well they do it while the rat is
sleeping but the hippocampus has a
connection to the neocortex which is
where learning takes place oh the red is
talking to itself to itself and is
storing away information that it's
gathered as it learned the maze and if
that doesn't happen no learning takes
place so we know just even recently a
little bit more about the mechanism then
it happens while you're sleeping and not
only that we know which phase because we
can see where the rat is it's in the
deep REM phase and sleep so people are
walking around sleep-deprived they don't
learn as well it's not some sort of
buzzy thing that we watch people and you
can actually wire up their brains and
watch those neurons fire it's incredibly
fast I mean I'm getting so excited
thinking about if I could start over
again I would go to medical school and I
would somehow be involved in studying
the brain it's just so intriguing any
good book tips for people who are
interested in it Brandon I know there is
people have talked about an interesting
book on on I think on the Twitter
podcast or something I don't remember
what the book was but they talked about
a relatively new book by some kind of
internet entrepreneur who wrote
something I don't know there are so many
because this area is expanding
exponentially it's a very fast growing
science and every day I subscribe to
Scientific American mind which gives me
a real quick overview and then it will
point to articles and those articles are
on the web so I can go out and read the
articles and I get a brain news letter I
mean there's just so much information
and it is all and you know what it ties
in directly everything I learn fits with
agile software development because one
thing I'm learning is that agile
software development does have some
pretty deep connections just as patterns
do that they they're good things because
they fit with the way we think with the
way we're hardwired with the way we
solve problems with the way we work
together it enhances all of that and
what the evolutionary biologists tell us
is that if you kind of move or operate
in sync with the way your brain is
structured you're gonna be not only more
effective you're gonna be happier you
can actually measure that look at the
chemicals dopamine yeah so that's
fascinating okay we have to we have to
stop where I'm actually literally
running out of recording time okay okay
so what
thank you very much Linda I think this
was very very useful and we'll we'll get
you back for this billeting stuff later
thanks for listening to software
engineering radio if you want more
information about the podcast and all
the other episodes visit our website and
SE - radio dotnet if you want to support
us you can donate to the SU radio team
by on the website or you can advertise
for su radio for example by clicking on
the Digg reddit delicious and slash note
buttons to contact the team leaves an
email to team and SI radio net or if
it's specific to an episode please use
the comments facility on the website so
other people can read and react to your
comments this episode of software
engineering radio as well as all other
episodes are licensed under Creative
Commons license please see the website
for details thanks to Charlie crowd and
the pot safe music network for the music
used in this show the song is called
Vegas hard rock shuffle